好的。那我们开始吧。
Okay. Yeah, let's get started.
感谢大家在下雨天还来参加。
Thanks for coming on a rainy day.
好的，很棒。那么我们现在在哪里呢？
Yeah. Cool. So where we are.
我记得上节课，
So I think last lecture,
我解释了为什么我们需要做并行化，对吧？
I justified why we need to do paralyzation, right?
因为我们确实需要更多的计算机和更多的内存，对吧？
Because we just need more computer and more memory, okay?
我想我还给大家讲解了什么是并行性，以及我们
And I think we also I also give you parole content explaining what are parallelisms and how we
如何将这种并行性应用到一个连续的图上，对吧？
can apply this kind of parallelisms onto a continued graph, right?
这会导致不同的运行时模式或通信模式，
It will result into different runtime pattern or communication pattern,
我们将在这节课中更深入地探讨这个问题。
and we are going to dive deeper into lecture, okay?
好的，总结一下，关于并行性，我们的问题表面上看，
Okay, just to recap, for parallelism, our problem superficially,
我们的问题基本上是如何在给定的设备类别上划分连续的计算图，对吧？
our problem is basically how to partition the continued graph on a given device class, right?
好吗？表面上我们会简化这个问题，然后我们会
Okay? Superficially, we are going to simplify this problem and we're going
一步步深入下去，好吗？
to go deeper and deeper, okay?
本课程中，基本上有两种
And there are essentially in this class, there are essentially two types of
并行方式，有明确的定义，一种是操作间并行，我们只是在图上切分，
parallelism which with a precise definition, one is interoperatism, where we just cut the graph,
不是在算子上切分，对吧？
not the operator, right?
另一种是操作内并行，我们是在算子上切分，但不是在图上切分。
And the other is intraparism, where we cut the operator but not the graph.
好的，我们就在NAS的讲座中停在这里。
Okay. And we stop here right in NAs lecture.
我认为这是NAS讲座中最重要的幻灯片之一。
I think this is one of the most important slide in NAS lecture.
我们通过每种类型的例子来讲解这两种分区方式，然后我们会发现，
We run through these two types of partism using example from each type, and we realize that
对于这种手术内的分区方式，我们总会引发某种通信，
for this kind of intraoperative partism, we will always cause some sort of communication,
我把这种通信称为连接性通信，明白吗？
which I call connective communication. Okay?
而对于第二种类型，也就是手术间的分区方式，它总会引发某种
And for the second type, which is the interop partism it always cause some type of
我们称之为PTP通信的通信。
communication which we call PTP communication.
好的，在这一页幻灯片上，
Okay. And in this slide,
我基本上给你举了两个设备的例子。
I basically give you an example of two devices.
为了加深你的理解，嗯，我不会只局限于这个例子。
To enhance your understanding, um, I'm not going to generalize a little bit.
我会把这个例子从两个设备、两个GPU推广到四个设备、四个GPU，好吗？
I'm going to generalize this from two devices, two GPUs to four devices, four GPUs, okay?
这样可以让你更好地理解到底发生了什么。
To give you a better understanding what is going on,
尤其是在沟通方面，因为就像我说的，沟通是最重要的事情
especially on communication part because like I said, communication is the most important thing
在分布式系统中，明白吗？
in poison, okay?
所以这是我们的案例，对吧？在这个双设备的场景下，我们按照那个图运行
So this is our case, right? In this two devices scenario, we run through that graph
遵循定义好的分区方式，然后我们在每个设备上得到两个部分和。
following the defined partitioning, and we get two partial sums on each device.
为了让每个设备上都有一个副本，我们要做的是运行双设备的 all-reduce，对吧？
And in order to get a replica on each devices, what we do is we run two device or reduce, right?
所谓双设备 all-reduce，就是第一个设备把它的部分和发送给
So by two device or reduce, I mean, the first device sends its partial sum to
第二个设备，然后第二个设备进行汇总。
the second device and the second device do summarization.
然后第二个设备把部分和发送给第一个设备，
And the second device, send partial sum to the first device and the
第一个设备也做同样的事情，对吧？这就是 all-reduce。
first device does the same thing, right? This is all reduce.
如果我们在四个设备上运行，也就是我们把这个图分成四份，
And if we run this on four devices, that is we partition this graph,
比如说分成四部分，我们切三次。
say in four parts, we cut three times.
好的。我们基本上会在每个设备上得到四分之一。
Okay. We'll get basically one fourth on device.
我们每个人得到的基本上就是这样，对吧？
What we all get is basically like this, right?
好的。所以每个设备都会得到一个部分和，但这个部分和
Okay. So each each of the four devices, we'll get a partial sum, but this partial sum
是总和的四分之一，对吧？
is one fourth of the total sum, right?
并且因为我们最后还是要应用这个部分和，
And because we still apply this partism that is in the end,
我们希望每个设备都有一个副本，对吧？
we want each device to have a replica, right?
所以这里其实是一样的，对吧？
So here, it's exactly the same, right?
我们需要在四个设备之间做一次全局归约。
We need to run or reduce across all four devices.
好的。而且这个归约显然比在两个设备上做归约要更耗费资源，对吧？
Okay. And this reduce is apparently more expensive than running or reduce on two devices, right?
因为要运行这个reduce，你只需要让每个设备
Because in order to run this reduce, all you need to do is you allow each device to
把它的部分和发送给所有其他设备，对吧？
send its partial sum to all other devices, right?
一旦设备收到所有的部分和，它就会进行聚合。
And once the device receives all the partial sums, it will do aggregation.
这就是为什么这种通信叫做reduce。
That is why this communication is called reduce.
它不是reduce，是all reduce。
It's not reduced. It's all reduce.
也就是说每个设备都需要通信并进行reduce，明白吗？
That is every device needs to communicate and reduce, okay?
从这个例子，你甚至可以推广到更多的设备，对吧？
And from this example, you can generalize even more to more devices, right?
随着你增加设备数量，随着你扩大用于训练模型的集群规模，
As you grow the lumber devices, as you grow the lumber the size of cluster you are
这个reduce操作会变得越来越昂贵，对吧？
going to use to train the model, this reduce is going to be more and more and more expensive, right?
它基本上是平方级别的复杂度，明白吗？
It's basically square square complexity, okay?
但相比之下，在这种解释主义中，无论你从哪里切，对吧，你都不会
But in contrast, uh, in this interperism, no matter where you cut, right, you are not going to
导致或减少集体通信。
cause or reduce or collective communication.
你只能让P之间进行通信。
You can only cause P to be communication.
也就是说，一个设备需要向另一个设备发送信息，对吧？
That is one device need to send to the other, right?
无论你怎么切，你可以垂直切，也可以水平切。
Notter how you cut, you can cut vertically or you cut horizontally.
但本质上，在这两个设备的场景下，你只需要一个设备
But essentially in this two device scenario, you just need one device to
向第二个设备发送一些东西。
send something to the second device.
而第二个设备不知道如何向第一个设备发送东西，对吧？
And the second device doesn't know how to send something to the first device, right?
好的，我希望这基本上能稍微提升你们的理解。好的，回到这张幻灯片，
Okay. I hope this basically enhance your understanding a little Okay, and come back to this slide,
我认为，之前我们主要在解释，嗯，是什么样的通信模式，
I think, previously we focused on explaining, um, what kind of communication pattern,
它会产生费用，对吧？
it will incur, right?
那么现在，让我们把注意力集中在设备上。
So now, let's focus on the uh on the device.
所以如果当时有任何设备的话。
So if there's any device at the time.
好吗？所以如果你再仔细看一下第一行，你会发现
Okay? So if you basically go through that, the first row one more time, you'll find that during
在整个比赛期间，所有设备都是忙碌的，对吧？
the entire lifetime of doing this competition, all devices are busy, right?
比如说，在这里，当你执行这个MthmoEdS的时候，完成metamo的一部分，当你执行这个memo时，
For example, here, when you do this MthmoEdS perform a part of metamo when you do this memo,
E设备完成memo的另一部分。
E device perform another part of memo.
基本上，任何时候这两个设备都是忙碌的，他们都在做一些工作。
Basically at anytime these two devices are busy, they're doing some work.
当你进行通信时，每个设备都在通信，对吧？
And when you do communication, each device are communicating, right?
好，那这个呢？在这种情况下，第一个设备会开始计算，
Okay. How about this one? So in this case, the first device will start compute,
对，它会产生它的缓存结果。
right, and it will produce its memo results.
但是在第一个设备计算的时候，第二个设备在做什么？
But during the computation of the first device, what is the second device doing?
它正在等待第一个设备发送结果。
It's waiting for the results to be sent from the first device.
所以这意味着如果第一个设备还没有完成计算，
So which means that if the first device haven't finished the compute,
那么第二个设备就是空闲的，对吧，就是在等待，和前面一样，对吧，
then the second device is idle, rights waiting, o same thing, right,
当我们继续操作时，就是第一个设备完成并把结果传递或发送给第二个设备，
when we proceed when the first device finished and forward results or send results to second device,
然后第二个设备才开始计算，对吗？
and then the second device start computing, right?
但问题是，在第二个设备计算的时候，第一个设备又是空闲的。
But the problem is during the second device compute, the first device is idle.
明白了吗？现在你能看出区别了吧？
Okay? Now, you'll see the difference, right?
第二个区别其实就是，在intraoperpism中，是的，
The second difference is basically, in intraoperpism, yes,
你将会触发一次非常昂贵的通信，但你可以始终让每个设备都保持忙碌。
you are going to trigger a very expensive communication, but you can always keep every device busy.
他们随时都在忙碌。
At anytime they are busy.
但在互操作主义中，是的，你可以在通信上做得更好，
But in interopism, yeah, you can do better on communication,
但你会遇到一个问题，就是当一些设备完成计算时，其他设备会处于空闲状态，因为他们
but you got a problem that is when some devices computed, the other devices are idle because they
正在等待结果。明白吗？
are waiting for the results. Okay?
这基本上是我想要强调的最重要的元点
This is basically the most important meta point
关于这两种主义我想表达的观点。
I want to make about these two types of pisms.
明白吗？我在这张幻灯片里做了总结。
Okay? Which I summarized in this slide.
嗯，所以基本上，临时互操作主义需要点对点通信，
Um, so basically interim interroparism requires point to point communication,
但它会导致设备空闲，对吧？
but it results in idle devices, okay?
但是对于互分主义，设备总是很忙，但你需要连接性的通信，对吧？
But for intero partism devices are always busy, but you require connective communication, okay?
如果我们把它们并排放在一起，我们基本上会得到这样一个表格，
And if we put them side by side, we basically get this table where,
对于互分主义，通信量较少。
for interpartism, the communication is less.
但是每次使用的设备数量更多，对吧？
Um, but the device at a time is more, okay?
而对于内分主义，通信量更多，因为它是连接性的。
And for intra partism the communication is more because it's connective.
但是每次使用的设备数量更少，对吧。
But the device at is less. Okay.
最终，你基本上会把所有这些分主义方式结合起来，你希望
Eventually, you are going to basically combine all this kind of parism and you want
基本上确保你在最小化通信的同时，也最小化每次使用的设备数量，对吧？
to basically make sure you minimize communication while minimize device at the time, right?
所以基本上你是在尝试解决这个问题。
So basically you're trying to solve this problem.
好的，在接下来的几节课中，
Okay. And in the next few lectures,
我会逐步地，嗯，深入地把这个问题转化成数学形式，这样你们就能明白我们在做什么了。
I'm going to gradually, like, uh, go deeper and deeper to formulate
这样你们就能理解我们在做什么了，无论是什么样的模型都适用，好吗？
this problem into a mathematical form so you can understand what we are doing
适用于所有不同类型的模型，明白吗？
for all different kind of models, okay?
但在我这么做之前，让我先总结一下这部分内容，好吗？
But before I do that, okay, let me summarize this part, okay?
这一点非常重要，就是我们如何表示不同类型的偏差。
This is very important. So the way that way represent the different types of partism.
我记得一开始我说过，传统上人们只讨论数据上的单一偏差，对吧？
I think at the beginning, I said, traditionally, people just talk about data on modo partism, right?
但在这门课上，我给你们一个新概念，就是互操作性偏差和内部偏差。
But in this class, I give you a new concept that is interop and into partism.
我想提出一个有力的论点，因为我认为，嗯，是的，
I want to make a strong argument because I think, uh, yeah,
数据偏差和模型偏差是非常经典的概念，但是，
data and modoparism are very classic concepts, but,
但是当你讨论这两个词的时候，其实也存在一些问题，对吧？
Um, but they have some problems when you talk about these two words, right?
对于数据划分，是的，这部分很清晰，对吧？
For data partism, yes, it's pretty clean, okay?
当我说数据划分时，你明白我的意思吧？
When I say data partism, you know what I mean, right?
我基本上是在数据上进行划分，然后进行复制等待，对吧？
I basically part in the data, I raplic wait, right?
但当我说多重划分时，这个词有点模糊，有点不明确，因为
But when I say Multi partarisms a little bit, like, ambiguous, a little bit vague, because
你可以做很多种多重划分。
there are so many types of multiparism you can do.
你可以划分图结构，你也可以划分操作符。
You can cut the graph, you can cut the operator.
也许从某种意义上说，数据划分也是一种多重划分，对吧？
And maybe in some sense, data partism is also a type of multipism right
如果你把整个数据看作一个大张量，对吧？
if you see the entire data as a big tenser, right?
所以你基本上是在批次维度上进行划分，对吧？
So you're basically partion over the batch dimension, okay?
这就是为什么我要引入这个新定义，打断一下，打断一下。
That's why I bring in this new definition interrupt interrupt.
我认为中断互操作性的定义非常以计算为中心。
And I think the definition of inter interop partism are very computational centric.
从某种意义上说，基本上当我说中断时，你知道，我不是中断算子，而是切断了计算图。
In a sense, basically when I say interrupt, you know, I'm not operator, but I'm just cut the graph.
当我说中断时，你知道，
And when I say interrupt, you know,
我是切断算子而不是计算图。
I'm cut the operator but not graph.
所以在接下来的讲座中，
So in the rest of lecture,
我可能会更多地使用这种定义方式，因为我觉得它非常精确。
I'm going to probably use more of this part of definition because I think it's very precise.
有什么问题吗？
Any problem about this?
很好，那我们继续。
Cool. Then let's continue.
好的，那么在这种新视角下，我们基本上可以尝试简化我们的问题，对吧。
Okay. Then under this new view, we can basically try to simplify our problem, right.
之前，我们的问题版本是需要对计算图进行划分。
Previously, the version of our problem is we need to partition the graph
在课堂上，大家都明白了，对吧？
over the class around the right, right?
现在我们基本上是在尝试找出最有效的方式来询问
And now we are basically trying to figure out what is the most efficient way to ask
如何通过结合内部和互操作性来对图进行处理。
you to the graph using a combination of inter and interoperabism.
你已经知道我的内部机制可以表示数据机制。
You already know that my interperism can represent datapism.
所以数据分区其实已经包含在这个句子里了，明白吗？
So data partism is already kind of like included in this sentence, okay?
当然，你还需要受到内存限制的约束，对吧。
And of course, you need to subject to memory constraints, right.
内存的意思是，当你进行分区时，你需要让模型适应设备，
Memory means that when you're partition, you need to fit that model into a device,
也就是让模型的一部分适应到一个设备上。
part of model into a device.
当然，你还需要受到通信约束的限制。
And of course, you need to subject to communication constraints.
但是在这里，我仍然觉得这个定义或者说这个表述
But here, I still feel this definition of all this statement of
这个问题仍然太复杂了，因为我觉得对于内存限制来说，
this problem is still too complicated, because I think for memory constraints,
这是有道理的，对吧。
it makes sense, right.
基本上你不能超过峰值内存。
You basically you cannot exceed the peak memory.
但对于通信来说，我说的受通信限制是什么意思，对吧？
But for communication, what do I mean by subject to communication constraints, right?
所以上一步是关于通信的，我说的通信是什么意思？
So the last step into communication, what do I mean by communication?
但在深入讨论通信之前，让我们先看一下这里最重要的目标。
But before I dive into communication, let's look at the most important objective here.
所以对于这个问题，最重要的目标是我们要高效，对吧？
So for this problem, the most important objective is we want to be efficient, right?
这始终是我们这门课的目标。
That is always always the goal of this entire class.
我们要高效，我们要尽可能快地计算，对吧？
We want to be efficient. We want to compute as fast as possible, right?
那么如果我们开始考虑这种划分方式，也就是我们运行
So then if we start considering this kind of partism that is we run
在超级大型集群上运行计算图时，我们如何定义效率？
a computer graph on a super large cluster, how do we define efficiency?
我觉得以前我们在单个设备上运行这种东西时，
I think previously when we run this kind of thing on single device,
我们已经有了效率的定义。
we already have a definition of efficiency.
基本上就是AI，也就是算术强度。
It's basically AI or arithmetic intensity.
我们希望每个算子都能最大化它的算术强度，也就是AI。
We want each operator to maximize his arithmetic intensity. So AI.
但AI更像是一种宏观层面的定义。
But AI is more like a macro level definition.
比如说，当你提到AI时，你可能实际上指的是
For example, when you speak AI, you probably when you talk about AI, you probably mean that
单个算子的原始强度，对吧？
the original intensity of single operator, right?
单个设备上的单一类型算子。
Single devices on single type of course.
好的。但在这里我们想要一个更偏向全局性的定义。
Okay. But here we want a definition that is more like a global,
更加全面，因为现在我们是在成千上万的GPU上运行一个图，我们如何衡量
more holistic because now we are running a graph on, say, thousands of GPUs, how we measure
这成千上万个GPU的总体效率，对吧？
the total efficiency of the thousands of GPUs, right?
我们还关心整个图的效率，而不是单个算子的效率。
And we also care about the entire graphs efficiency instead of a single operator.
好吗？那么，为了引入这种效率，
Okay? So, in order to introduce this efficiency,
我需要介绍一个非常重要的术语，好吗？
I need to introduce a very important term, okay?
这个术语基本上，如果你去工业界，
And this term is basically, uh, if you go to industry,
所有人都在谈论这个术语，好吗？
so everybody is talking about this term, okay?
它叫做MF。
So it's called MF.
MFU。如果你阅读任何关于语言模型系统、效率或者相关论文，
MFU. If you read any language model system or efficiency or any paper,
他们都会报告MFU，因为
they're going to report MFU because
MFU 基本上是一种展示你公司系统团队实力的方式。
MFU is basically a way to show the kind of the strength of the system team in your company.
如果你的系统团队很强，他们应该能给出很高的 MFU。
If your system team is pretty good, uh, they should give a pretty good MFU
因为任何公司的系统团队，比如 open air，他们的工作
because the job of the entire system team in any company, for example, open air, their job
基本上就是最大化 MFU。
is basically maximize MFU.
好吗？那么 MFU 是什么呢？
Okay? So what is MFU, okay?
这里我直接给你定义。
So here I directly give you the definition.
MFU 等于浮点运算次数。
So MFU equals to the number of flops.
这里我用一个小写的 S。
So here I use a smaller S, okay.
这里我用一个大写的 S，我想稍微区分一下。
And here I use a capital S, and I want to distinguish it a little bit.
当我这样做时，你可以看到它基本上就是很多浮点运算。
So when I do this, you can see it's basically that the lumber flops, a lot of flops.
这里的flops数量基本上指的是完成你的机器学习程序所需的总计算浮点操作数。
And the number of flops here basically means the total compute flowing point opera
也就是说，完成你的机器学习程序需要的计算量。
is needed to finish your machine learning program.
好吗？所以MFU等于flops数量除以时间T，T是花费的时间，
Okay? So MFU equals to number of flops divided by the time T and T is time spent,
比如说，用来完成训练的时间，或者说当推理基本完成你的任务时。
um on finishing finishing training, for example, or when interingt basically finish your job.
然后再除以峰值flops。
And divided by the peak flops.
这里我用大写字母，表示这是一个单词。
Here, I use capitals, meaning that this is a single word.
好的，这里的flops大写S表示芯片或GPU的处理能力。
Okay, these flops capital S means the processing capability of a chip or GPU.
比如，你可能知道V100的flops大写S基本上大约是150 flops，对吧？
For example, you probably know that V 100, the flops capital S is basically around 150 flops, right?
呃，T flops，对，抱歉。
Um, T flops, sorry, yeah.
也就是说是每秒一万亿次浮点运算，T flops每秒，明白了吗？
There's a Terra Okay, T flops per second, okay?
所以在这里，从这个图表你可以看到MF基本上是一个百分比，对吧？
So here, from this cavity you can see MF is basically a percentage, right?
好的。所以这里的MFU代表模型浮点运算UTS加成，就是UTS加成。
Okay. So MFU here stands for model flops UTS addition, and it is UTS addition.
它基本上描述了你能利用GPU峰值性能的百分比。
It basically characterize how much percentage you can utilize your peak capability of your GPUs.
明白吗？因为你的GPU一旦制造出来，你买了GPU之后
Okay? Because your GPU once it is manufactured and you bought a GPU are you
基本上就有一个GPU能达到的峰值浮点运算能力，每一代新的GPU峰值更高。
basically have a peak flops that the GPU can enable, every generation nearer GPU have higher peak.
但是你的程序并不能总是用到峰值浮点运算能力，因为你
But your program cannot always use peak flops because you
会用到不同的操作，而不同的操作有不同的计算特性，
use different operations and different operations have different computation charistics also,
你也可能写出很糟糕的代码，这样你的代码就会变慢。
you can write pretty bad code and your code could be slowed.
这就是为什么你的MFU不能总是达到峰值，明白了吗？
That's why your MFU canot always reach peak, okay?
好的，从这里你可以看到
Okay. From here, you can see
MF 是一个单位，表示数值在 0 到 100% 之间。
MF is a udtion which means that the value is 0-100%.
明白了吗？这里的 flops 已经解释过了，就是计算你的模型所需的总计算量。
Okay? And here, the flops already explained it is a total compute needed to compute your model.
明白了吗？那么，如何估算这个值呢？
Okay? Uh So how to estimate this?
比如说，如果你的模型是 methemo，你已经知道怎么估算了，对吧？
For example, if your model is a methemo you already know how to estimate, right?
就是两个 M k。我给你公式，好吗？
It's two M k. I give you the equation, okay?
但如果你的模型是 lotto，你就需要把它们加在一起，对吧？
But if your model is a lotto, you'll be add together, right?
这是每次迭代计算模型所需的总 flop。
It's a total flop needed for computer model for iteration, okay?
所以这个术语基本上描述了运行程序需要多少计算机资源，对吧？
So this term basically characterize how many computer needed to run the program, okay?
这个很容易理解。
And this is easy to understand.
也就是说，当你编写程序、编写软件的时候，
That is when you write your program when you write your software,
当你在GPU上部署这个程序和软件时，你运行迭代并进行基准测试。
and when you deploy this program and software on GPU, you run Iteration and you do a benchmark
你知道这个T基本上就是所需的时间。
and you know how long it takes this T is basically how long it takes.
明白吗？如果你用这个数字除以T，你基本上就能知道你的程序运行得有多好，
Okay? If you divide this number by T, you basically get how good your program is running,
以每秒浮点运算次数来衡量。
in terms of flops per second.
比如，你可以每秒运行100次浮点运算。
For example, you can run at 100 flops per second.
这就是你的代码能达到的性能。
That is how good you can achieve on your code.
然后你用这个数字除以GPU所能提供的峰值浮点运算次数，
And then you divide this number by the peak flops offered by the GPU,
这就是加法。明白了吗？
that is addition. Okay. Does that make sense?
很好。这个术语非常重要，所以我花了很多时间来解释它。
Cool. And this term is so important, so I spent a lot of time explaining this.
明白了吗？所以你可以看到，在这门课上，我们试图构建马赫系统，对吧？
Okay? So as you can see, in this class, we try to build marchearing systems, right?
MSU基本上就是判断你的机器学习系统好坏的标准。
And MSU is basically the verdict of whether your marche learning system is good.
对吧？如果你的机器学习系统很差，你的MFU就会很低，对吧？
Right? If your machine learning system is pretty bad, your MFU is going to be low, right?
这意味着在相同的程序下，你的运行时间会比别人长，对吧？
Which means that given the same program, you are going to run longer than others, right?
如果你的MF很高，那说明你在数据增强方面做得很好。
And if your MF is high, that means you are doing pretty good job on augmentation.
你基本上是在CPU上榨取最后一丝性能。
You are basically squeeze the last bit of performance on the CPU.
好的，有关于这个术语的问题吗？
Okay. Any question about this term?
很好。那么我们如何获得这些Pi flops，其实很简单，对吧？
Cool. So how we get these Pi flops, it's very easy, right?
你只需要去查一下
You just go check
ND产品手册，ND会给你这个数值。
ND products back and ND will give you the number.
比如说，这里就是T100产品手册，好吗？
For example, this is the t hundred products back here, okay?
就像我说的，当你训练语言模型时，你基本上是在LP 16, 1004上运行，对吧？
And if you are like I said, when you train language model, you basically run on LP 16, 1004, right?
所以你基本上是检查这一行，对吧？
So you basically check this line, right?
你可以看到P
And you can see the P
161004有这种峰值浮点运算能力。
161004 have this kind of peak flops.
明白了吗？这意味着你需要把这个值代入这里。
Okay? Which means that you need to substitute this value into here.
好的，明白。是的。
Okay. Cool. Yeah.
但这并不总是反映真实的性能。
Doesn't always rect real performance.
当你在比较其他数值存储时，是的，没错。
When you're comparing compare other number stores, Yeah, exactly.
你把它和另一个系统做对比，比如说。
You compare it to another system, for example.
好的，我会告诉你我们现在的进展。
Yeah, I will tell you where we are now.
我的意思是，比如说，看看open eye今天的表现。
I mean, for example, how open eye is doing today.
好的。但就像我说的，媒体只会给你展示峰值的浮点运算能力。
Okay. But like I said, media only gives you the peak flops.
这个峰值浮点运算能力其实是你很难真正达到的。
The Pk flops is nowhere you can achieve.
因为它有非常严格的要求。
Because it has a very strong requirement.
比如说，对于逐元素操作，你是无法达到峰值浮点运算能力的，
For example, for element wise operations, you are not going to achieve the P flops,
因为你无法通过逐元素操作来充分利用所有的核心。
because it's not you not be able to use element wise to utilize all their course.
基本上，为了达到那个峰值浮点运算能力，
And basically, in order to achieve that peak flops, uh,
有一种方法，就是你做一个非常大的矩阵乘法运算。
there's one way that is you do a very big Mtmo.
媒体基本上可以有代码或者详细说明来实现峰值浮点运算能力。
And media can basically have the code or elaborate to achieve P flops.
但这个前提只适用于矩阵运算。
But only subject that only applies to met.
但是当我谈到这个程序时，对吧，这个程序的浮点运算能力，其实如你所想的那样并不高，
But when I talk about this program, right, this program flops, as you can imagine,
在transformers中，你只有很少的矩阵乘法操作。
in transformers, you only have a few metamo.
而在矩阵乘法之间，你有很多层归一化和一些softmax操作，
And between metamo you have many layer normalization and a few softmax,
而这些操作的效率比矩阵乘法要低。
and these kind of operations are less efficient than Mtmo.
所以当你把整个机器学习程序作为一个整体来看时，
So when you consider the entire machine learning program as a whole,
你无法达到峰值的浮点运算能力。
you are not able to achieve the peak flops.
好的，有什么问题吗？
Okay. Any question about this?
很好，那么，给定这个公式，
Cool. Yeah, then, given this equation,
我假设你们都理解这个公式了。
I assume you understand this equation.
我们再多讨论一点，好吗？
Let's discuss a little bit more, right?
在TP商业程序中，哪些潜在因素会降低MF？
What are basically in a TP Commercial program, what are the potential factors that can lower MF?
因为MF的最大可能值基本上是100%，对吧？
Because the maximum possible value of MF is basically 100%, right?
但我告诉过你，我们达不到那个值，明白吗？
But I told you we are not going to get there, okay?
那么，究竟有哪些潜在因素阻止我们实现100%的MF？
So what are the potential factors that basically prevent us from achieving 100% MF?
好，第一个当然是操作类型。
Okay. So the first one is, of course, operator types.
就像我说的，对于matmul，你是有机会的。
Like I said, for met Mo, you have a chance.
如果你只运行matmul，你有机会获得峰值性能。
If you only run met Moe you have a chance to get peak performance.
但在计算程序中，你会有很多逐元素操作，比如，
But in machining programs, you have many element wise, for example,
alo、gelo、arm addition，这些都不是matmul。
alo gelo, arm edition, which are not matm.
那为什么这种逐元素操作无法达到峰值flops呢？
So why this kind of element wise cannot get peak flops?
你基本上要回到那个算术强度的问题。
You basically go back to that arithmetic intensity.
你需要读取所有数据，才能计算一个算子。
You need to read all the data in order to compute one operator.
但对于metam，你只需要读取两个矩阵，就能执行大量的浮点运算。
But for metam, you just need to read two matrix and you can perform a lot of flops.
所以你的AI在
So your AI is much higher on
Metamor上比其他算子高得多，对吧？
Metamor compared to other operators, okay?
这意味着有一些好的模型。
So this means that there are some good models.
也有一些不好的模型，对吧？
There are some bad models, right?
因为如果一个模型总是用逐元素操作，而不用metam，那就是个糟糕的模型。
Because if a model always has element wise, but not metamos bad model.
从GPU加法的角度来看是这样。
Right from the perspective of GPU addition.
但如果一个模型在metamO和其他操作之间有完美的平衡，
Okay? But if a model has a perfect balance of metamO and something else,
这样你就可以在很好地利用你的GPU的同时，达到一个平衡，对吧，并且提升
then you can strike a balance between, utilize your GPU pretty good, right, and increase
机器学习模型的基本能力，对吧？
the marchine learning models basically power, right?
因为你不能总是让你的模型只做数学运算，因为那样只能进行线性操作。
Because you cannot always do matm for your model because it will only bear linear operations.
线性操作在机器建模能力上是非常有限的，对吧？
Linear operation has very limited kind of marchinary modeling power, right?
所以一个完美的模型基本上应该在自身能力之间达到平衡。
So a perfect model should basically strike a balance between its own power.
比如说，你需要混合线性操作和非线性操作来表达
For example, you need to mix linear operations and nonlinear operations to express
足够复杂的函数。
a sophisticated enough functions.
并且你还需要有一种方法能够很好地利用GPU。
And you need to basically have a way to utilize GPU pretty well.
好吗？所以这里我想呼应一下我第一节课讲的内容。
Okay? So here I want to echo a little bit in my first lecture.
我也想呼应一下我们的嘉宾讲者说的内容，对吧？
I also echo what our guest speaker said, right?
所以最终在当前的现代机器学习模型开发中，当你设计模型时，
So eventually in the current in contemporary machinery development, you when you design model,
你必须考虑到这一点，明白吗？
you have to think about this. Okay?
你不能只设计你觉得还不错的模型。
You cannot design model that you think are pretty good.
有很多代表性能力，比如模型可以拟合任意函数，但它对GPU并不友好。
A lot of representative power, like model arbitrary function, but it's not GPU friendly.
你必须考虑到这一点。
Okay, you have to think about this.
你需要最大化你的MF，设计你的模型，明白吗？
Okay, you need to maximize your MF well, design your model, okay?
这就是为什么transformer会胜出的原因，对吧？
That's why transformer wins, right?
好的，很棒。
Okay. Cool.
我已经告诉过你，哪些操作对MF友好，哪些对O和M不友好。
Uh, I already told you, what are the MF friendly O and M unfriendly op.
基本上，MTM对MF非常友好，而元素级操作则不是很友好。
So basically MTM is very MF friendly, um, and element we are not very friendly.
很好。当然，你的MMF会受到哪些影响？
Cool. Okay, of course, what kind of affect your MMF?
那就是你在加工程序中应用的系统增强，对吗？
That is the system ogmentation you applied to your machining program, right?
如果你做这些，比如图增强、融合，
If you do telling, if you do all these kind of like graph ogmentation, you do fusion, you do
还有低精度计算，对吧？
lower precision, uh, computation, right?
这样你确实可以减少读取数据所花的时间，
And you can definitely, uh, reduce the time you spend on reading data,
但会增加你在计算上花的时间，对吧？
but increase the time you spend on, um, on computing, right?
你也可以让你的GPU比以前更忙碌。
And you can always keep your GPU busier than before.
所以如果你知道如何优化你的程序，如何优化你的图，
So if you know how to optimize your program, how to optimize your graph,
如何优化你的算子，你就能提升你的MMF，明白吗？
how to optimize your operators, you are going to increase your MMF. Okay?
所以我让你们在第二次作业中做的，其实就是这些。
So what I ask you to do in the second homework is basically,
我希望你能提高你的MF，好吗？
I hope you can increase your MF, okay?
第三个主要影响MMF的因素，基本上当然是精度，对吧？
And the third factor primary factor that affect MMF is basically, of course, precision, right?
因为对于GPO来说，在不同的精度下有不同的峰值浮点运算能力。
Because for GPO, it has a different peak flops at different precision.
这意味着如果你使用不同的精度，这个数值是不同的。
Which means that this number is different if you use different um precision.
明白了吗？当然，还有类型，对吧？
Okay? And of course, the type of course, right?
我给你展示了H100的产品。
I show your products back of H 100.
所以它们在十进制和长十进制下有不同的峰值浮点运算能力，好吗？
So they have different peak flops for ten circle and long ten circle, okay?
GPO类型的H100绝对比E100更强大。是的。
GPOtype H 100 is definitely more powerful than E 100. Yeah.
所以一旦这个数值发生变化，这个数值也会跟着变，
So this number is going to change once this number changes, you know,
你的MF也会随之变化，好吗？还有其他问题吗？
your MF is going to change, okay? Anything else?
基本上，这又回到了我们本节课的主要内容——通信，对吧？
Basically, it goes back to our main content of this lecture, communication, right?
所以当你开始做部分加法时，你就引入了通信。
So when you start doing part addition, you introduce communication.
一旦你开始通信，这意味着你要把时间花在其他事情上，
And once you communicate, that means you're going to spend time on something else,
但不是在TPU上，从整体来看，你实际上是在降低M，因为这个值会增加。
but not on TPU, holistically, you are basically lowering M because this is going to increase.
通信是需要时间的。我们有哪些可能的方法可以减少通信呢？
Communication takes time. What are the possible ways that we can reduce communication?
有几种方法，对吧。第一种是，你选择一种能够最小化通信的范式。
There are a few ways, right. One is, you choose the paradim in a way that minimize communication.
你不要做连接操作。
You don't do connective.
你做的连接操作要比PDP少。
You do less connective compared to PDP.
第二种是，你尽量把那些开销大的通信放在高带宽互连上。
Second is, you try to put those expensive communication on high bandwis interconnect.
对，我们接下来会讲这个，好吗？
Right. And we are covered next, okay?
当然，你也可以进行一些调度，
And of course, you can also do some scheduling to make
确保你的通信和计算是重叠进行的。
sure your communication is overlapped with compute.
这样一来，你基本上就能减少通信时间，对吧？同时我们会提升MF。
That way, you can basically diminish the time of communication, right? And we'll increase MF.
好的，这样基本上就给你一个整体的概念。
Okay. So that basically give you a high level picture.
所以当我们开始考虑并行化时，呃，我们的问题就会变得更复杂一些
So when we start considering paralyzation, uh, our problem becomes a little bit more complicated
因为这里又多了一个因素，就是通信。
because there's one more factor here, communication.
好的。好的，为了同步一下，嗯，
Okay. Okay, so to synchronize a little bit, um,
我想在之前所有的课程里，我们都讲过如何确保
I think in all previous lecture, we explain how to make sure
这三个要素都得到了处理，对吧？
the three items are being taken care of, right?
所以基本上在接下来的课程中，
And so basically in the rest of the lecture,
我现在要开始讨论沟通，因为这是
I'm going to start discussing communication because that's
我们在进行部件添加后引入的一个新因素。
a new factor we introduced once we do part addition.
好的，但在那之前，
Okay. But before that,
我还想再花一点时间讲讲MFU。
I still want to spend a little bit more time on MFU.
现在假设你开始工作了，你的老板会让你来问我
So now, suppose you start working okay and your boss is going to ask you to ask me
你加工程序的MF。你会怎么做？
MF of your marchining program. What do you do?
有什么流程？因为我觉得这将来某一天肯定会发生在你身上。
What's the procedure? Because I think this will happen someday in the future, yeah for you.
B MF是衡量你使用RTP水平的重要方式，对吧。
B MF is such an important way to measure how good you are using the RTP right.
比如说，如果你让你的老板买
For example, if you ask your boss to buy
多个TPU，你就需要一个合理的理由。
Mul TPUs, you need justification.
然后你的老板会问你，
And your boss will ask you,
好的，你在使用RTPU方面有多厉害？
Okay, how good you are using RTPU?
如果你只用了MF的20%，那不行，我会拒绝你。
If it's the only 20% of MF, no, I'm going to reject you.
但如果你已经达到了50%，
But if you're already at 50%,
我会为你买更多的GPU，对吧？
I'm going to buy more GPU for you, right?
好的。那么，如何向我询问MF呢？
Okay. So how to ask me MF?
这里有几个步骤，好吗，
So there are a few steps, okay,
我会一一讲解，而且我也会把这个作为作业布置下去。
I'm going to go through, and I'm also going to put this in homework.
好的。你必须要做这些，而且你需要写
Okay. You have to do this, and you need to write
尤其是针对语言模型的编程。
the programming especially for language models. Okay.
所以第一步，当然是看你的机器学习程序，
So the first step, of course, you look at your machine learning program,
然后你统计这里有多少个操作。
and you count how many ops here.
你还要试着弄清楚你的数据的形状。
And you also try to figure out the shape or your data.
有了这些数据形状和操作类型，基本上
And so with this data shapes with the type of operators and so basically
图中所有的操作，你都可以估算出
all the operators that in that graph, you are able to estimate, uh the total flops needed to
运行一次前向和反向传播所需的总浮点运算量。
run one iteration of forward and backward.
因为你知道计算本质上就是大量的矩阵乘法，对吧？
Because you know the computes essentially a lot of math mol linear, right?
所以你基本上要统计需要多少次加法和浮点运算
So you basically count how many addition and basically floating point arithmetics
来运行这个目标计算图。
you need for running the tar graph.
这样你就得到了第一个参数，也就是flops。
So you all get the first term, which is flops.
好吗？然后假设你已经有了你的系统，比如说你的作业一，对吧？
Okay? And then suppose you already have your system, for example, your homework one, right?
你是在不同的库里写的，对吧？
You wrote at difference in library, right?
你可以运行一次transformer的前向和反向传播。
You can run the transformer for one iteration, forward and backward.
然后你在你的目标GPU类型上运行，基本上就是测试一下需要多长时间，对吧？
And you run on your target type of GPU and you basically try to benchmark how long it takes, right?
这样你就知道运行需要多长时间了
And that give you since that how long it takes for running
当它在你的系统上运行这个程序时。
while it using your system, for this program.
你得到了第二个时间T，明白了吗？
You get a second term T. Okay?
第三，当然，你要去英伟达的网站，查看他们的产品规格。
And third, of course, you go to Media's website, you check their product spec.
比如说，如果你在作业二里用的是T4，
You check, for example, if you are running on T four in homework two,
或者将来你用的是H100，你就要查查它们的P flops等参数。
or if you are running on H hundred in future, you check their P flops and
你要确保你确实使用了核心。
you make sure that you indeed use the core.
比如说，P16核心，或者他们在规格中提到的。
For example, a P 16 core or they mentioned in the spec.
你基本上会得到第三个术语，也就是P flops，对吧？
You basically get a third term which is the P flops, right?
然后你就可以计算MF了。
And then you are able to calculate MF.
你会知道你对GPU的利用率是多少百分比。
You'll know how many percentage you utilize for the GPU.
好的，所以我要把这个作为作业。
Okay. So I'm going to put this into homework.
好的，我要给你一个ama。
Okay, I'm going to give you ama.
我要把amas还给你们。
I'm going to give you amas back.
所以Lama有很多层，就像我为GBD ray展示的表格一样。
So Lama has many layers like the table I showed for GBD ray.
好的，我基本上定义了有多少层、每一层的transformer层数，以及每一层的形状。
Okay. I basically defines how many layers, transformer layers for each layer, what's the shape?
我会给你一个ama，你告诉我训练ama需要多少flops，以及训练ama需要多少flops。
I'm going to give you ama, and you tell me the lamas flops, how much flops you needed to train ama.
好吗？然后我会给你一个程序，你估算一下训练Llama IT所需的MMF。
Okay? And then I'm going to give you a program, and you estimate the MMF for training Llama IT.
好吗？好的。接下来我会简化一下。
Okay? Yeah. Mix I'm going to simplify.
你只需要考虑FP16。对，对。
You only consider FP 16. Yeah, yeah.
好的，因为大部分的计算都是在FP16核心上完成的。
Okay. Yeah, because the majority of compute takes place on IP 16 course.
只有很少的计算是在FP32核心上完成的。
Just a little bit compute takes place on IP 32 course.
明白了吗？好的，那么为什么这个这么重要？
Okay? Okay, so why this is so important?
因为下周我们开始接触skinning lows的时候，
Be Because in next week when we start touching base on skinning lows and you start
你会意识到人们设计网络，尤其是设计语言模型的方式，
to realize that the way that people design your networks especially design language models is all
基本上都是围绕这个MF和flop来展开的。
basically anchored on this MF and flop scene.
好吗？我待会儿会更深入地讲解，好吗？
Okay? And I'm going to dive deeper later, okay?
嗯，所以重复一下，
Uh, so to repeat,
MF 正在成为当今语言模型行业中一个高度关注的指标，好吗？
MF is becoming a metric, highly indexed in today's language model industry, okay?
我会给大家一些真实的数据。
And I'm going to give you a few real numbers.
基本上四年前，我们的集群主要由 V100 组成，
So basically four years ago, our class is mainly composed of the V 100,
也就是说基本上是领先两代的设备，好吗？
so basically two generations ahead, okay?
抱歉，是落后两代，嗯，所以最好的机器学习系统运行在，比如说，
Two generation before, sorry, um, so the best machine learning system running on, for example,
V100 基本上只能达到 MMF 的 30% 到 50%。
1,100 can basically get 30 to 50% of MMF.
也就是说我们只利用了 GPU 一半的性能。
Okay, that is we only utilize half of the power of our GPU.
好吗？这是在 V100 上表现最好的系统。
Okay? The best system, okay, on Viva hundred.
你可以看到这里，VA100的峰值浮点运算能力基本上是112万亿次每秒，对吧，Tera Flops。
And you can see here the peak flops for Va hundred is essentially 112 T flops, right, Terra flops,
这意味着四年前，我们每块GPU在120亿参数的语言模型上只能用大约50到60万亿次每秒的算力。
which means that four years ago, we can only use like almost 50 to 60 T flops
每块GPU只能用在120亿参数的语言模型上。
per GPU on class, 120 language model.
当然，Mchani系统在发展，硬件也变得更强大了，对吧？
Of course, Mchani system is developing and hardware is also getting more powerful, right?
快进到Eva100，我们基本上达到了30%的MFU。
So fast forward to Eva hundred, uh, we basically get 30% of MFU.
好吗？其实不是很理想。
Okay? Not very good.
好的，一旦Flash Attention出来后，我们可以达到60%。
Okay. And once flash attention is out, we can get to 60%.
现在你知道为什么Flax这么重要了吧？
So now you know why flax is so important, right?
这基本上意味着你能节省数十亿美元。是的。
It basically means that you just save billions of dollars. Yeah.
好的，所以一旦有了Flash Attention，我们基本上可以从30%提升到60%。
Okay. Uh, so once how fly ation, we can basically boost from 30% to 6%.
好吗？而且60%已经相当不错了。
Okay? And 60% is already pretty good.
就像我说的，你唯一能达到100%的方法，
Like I said, the only way you can achieve
就是你只运行matm，什么都不做。
100% is that you only run matm, nothing else.
但在这里你已经能达到60%，这已经很不错了。
But here you already get 60%, which is pretty good.
好的，给你一个参考，P30、P16、A100的峰值flops基本上是312，
Okay. And to give you a reference, the peak flops of P 30 P 16, tircle of A 100 is basically 312,
这意味着我们已经能在每个E100上运行接近160的flops了，好吗？
which means that we can already run at almost 160 flops per E 100, okay?
最近，我们都在把集群从E100迁移到H100，对吧？
And recently, we are all moving our cluster from E 100 to H 100, right?
所以我们表现会稍微差一点，因为
So so we are becoming a little bit worse because
H100的峰值flops要高得多。
HI hundred peak flop is much higher.
而我们的软件还没有跟上，所以我们只能运行在30%到50%之间。
Okay, and our software is not catching up, so we can only run between 30% to 50%.
好的。所以基本上，如果你在一家公司工作，并且你们公司的系统运行在它的范围内，
Okay. So basically, if you work for a company and your company system is running within its range,
你就不会被解雇。
you are not going to be fired.
好的。但如果低于30，你就有问题了。
Okay. But if it's below 30, you have a problem.
明白吗？而这为什么取决于模型的大小？
Okay? And why is that is depending on model size?
显然，运行更大的metamol会比运行
Apparently, running larger metamol will be more efficient than running
小的metamR更高效。运行更大的metamol会给你更高的MF。
small metamR Running larger metamol will give you a higher MF.
所以如果你训练一个非常大的模型，你会达到50%。
So if you train a really big model, you're going to hit 50% one.
但如果你用一个更小的模型，你只能达到30%，明白吗？
But if you to a smaller model, you hit you're going to get 30%, okay?
供你参考，t hundred有992 flops，这意味着我们可以利用
And for your reference, at hundred has 992 flops, which means that we can utilize we can operate at
对于t hundred来说，每个GPU几乎可以达到300 flops。
almost 300 flops per GPU for t hundred.
嗯，关于什么是分割因素。是的。
Yeah. About what is dividing factor. Yeah.
在之前，检测器有哪些因素？
In the previous what are the things that detector?
主要因素是什么？
What is the major factor?
为什么是模型架构？
Why is model architecture?
如果你用transformer，你不会达到100。
If you do transformer, you're not going to hit 100.
除非你能发明一个只用数学的模型，但那个模型会非常弱，
Unless you can invent a model that is only matma, but that model will be super weak
因为它只有线性操作。
because it only have linear openon.
另一个因素是通信，因为你要在成千上万甚至一万台
The other is communication because you are going to run this on thousands or 10,000
GPU上运行，这些通信会花时间。
GPs and those communication takes time.
它会让事情变慢。好吧，显然今年，英伟达承诺会推出B 100，
I slows down things. Okay. Apparently, this year, media promised to shape B 100,
嗯，我想猜一下。好的。
uh, I would like to take a guess. Okay.
在作业三中，我会要求你写一篇论文。
And in Homework three, I'm going to ask you to write the essay.
好的，这是一个开放性问题。
Okay. It's open problem.
我会给你们几个开放性问题。
I'm going to give you a few open problems.
比如说，有一个开放性问题是让你们猜测B上的MF会是多少。
For example, one open problem you make a guess of what MF will be on B
有100个计算器，你需要提供证据。
100 clacers and you need to provide evidence.
你需要进行论证和说明理由。
You need to argue, justify it.
好的，酷。好，还没结束。
Okay. Cool. Okay, not finished yet.
我还需要补充一些与MF相关的内容。
I still need to in something relative to MF.
好吗？所以除了MF，我们还有另一个概念叫做HF。
Okay? So besides MF, we have another concept called HF.
好的，这里HFU，MU是一样的，对吧，都是浮点运算利用率，但H代表硬件。
Okay, HFU here, MU is the same, right, flops utilization, but H stands for hardware.
所以为了区分，我们关注MF，也关注HF。
So to distinguish it we care about MF, we care about HF.
所以SUFU其实是更容易理解的定义。
So SUFU is actually more easy to understand definition.
它基本上是从硬件层面精确描述的，你有多少个ti。
It's basically precisely characterized from hardware level, how many ti you have.
比如说，这个硬件有，
For example, this hardware have say,
1,000个浮点运算，你的程序在硬件层面每秒利用了600个浮点运算。
1,000 flops and your program, uh, like on the hardware level, utilizes 600 flops per second.
那么你的HF就是60%。
Then your HF is 60%.
那么既然有HUFU，为什么还要有MFU？
Then given HUFU why there is a MFU?o?
问题在于，如果你还记得紧急程序的话，在内存部分，对吧，我们有
The problem is, if you still remember emergeny programs, but in the memory part, right, we have
一些可以把计算机当作内存来处理的小技巧。
some tricks that we can treat a computer for memory.
还记得那个检查点的事情吧？
Still remember the checkpointing thing, right?
所以我们可以在transformer的边界设置几个检查点，然后在反向传播时，
So we can checkpoint a few at the trasfmer boundary, and during the backward,
我们可以重新计算，对吧？
we can recompute, right?
实际上这种优化方式的问题在于，你实际上需要花费
The problem actually MFU of that kind of optimization is you actually spend
额外的计算量来节省一些内存。
extra flops in order to save some memory.
而这些额外的计算量其实并没有真正推动
And this extra flops is not actually contributing to the progress of
模型训练的进展。这样说有道理吗？
the model training. Does that make sense?
好的。这意味着你需要花费额外的计算量，或者
Okay. Which means that you need to spend extra flops or
做一些其他的事情，而这些其他的事情其实是没有意义的。
something else and something else is meaningless.
这就意味着你的TPU实际上是在一个非常高的利用率下运行的。
Which means that your TPU is actually operated at a very high tition level.
但是因为你花费了额外的计算量，
But because you spend that amount of extra flops,
你的MF实际上是相当低的。你明白我的意思吧？
your MF is actually pretty low. You got my point, right?
这意味着你其实还是在浪费钱，
Which means that you're still wasting money because
因为最终你的OKR是让模型收敛。
eventually your OKR is training the model to converge.
这并不像是在节省内存，对吧？
It's not like saving memory, right?
好的，这就是为什么有HF的原因，明白了吗？
Okay. So that's why there is HF, okay?
并且已经解释过在什么情况下，
And already explained in what case,
HFU不等于MF，就是你花了一些计算量在其他工作上，而这些工作
HFU does not equal to MF, that is you spend some flops for other work, and that work is not
并没有帮助你的模型收敛。
contributing to your model convergence.
明白了吗？就像我说的，在硅谷，人们只关注MF。
Okay? So like I said, in Silicon Valley, people only index on MF.
所以如果你的老板问你什么是保留率，你不能报告HF，因为HF
So if your boss asks what's retention, you cannot report HF because HF is
有时候并不等于MF，明白吗？
sometimes is not equal to MF, okay?
嗯，我可以再问一个问题吗？
Um, I can ask one more question.
所以如果我们在策略中使用这种检查点，对吧，我们在transumer边界做检查点，
So if we use those kind of checkpoint in strategy, right, we checkpoint at the transumer boundary,
那么HU和MF之间的数学关系是什么？
then what is the mathematical relation between HU and MF?
有人想回答吗？好吧，让我来解释一下。
Anyone want to answer? Okay. Let me explain.
其实这个很容易理解，对吧？
So it's very easy to understand, right?
所以没有检查点时，你基本上做一次前向和一次反向，对吧？
So without checkpointing, you basically perform one forward and went backward, right?
而有了检查点，我想我在课上解释过，
And with checkpointing, I think I explained in the lecture,
你会做两次前向和一次反向。
you perform two forward and went backward.
那你其实是在比较两件事，对吧。
Then you are basically comparing two things, right.
一种是你做一次前向和一次反向，对吗？
One is you perform one forward and one backward, right?
另一种是你做两次前向和一次反向。
And the other you perform two forward and one backward.
那它们之间是什么关系呢？
So what are the relation?
所以本质上，在大多数神经网络训练中，我们可以认为一次反向等于两次前向。
So essentially, in most near training, we can think that one backward equals to two forward.
有人能解释为什么吗？
Can anyone explain why?
如果你要对参数和激活值求梯度，基本上对于大多数数学运算，
If you are going to take grads against the parameters and activations, basically for most math,
你在反向传播时基本上做了两倍于前向传播的计算。
you basically do twice during backward, compared to forward.
明白了吗？所以如果我们把这个代入公式，没有做检查点的时候，
Okay? So if we substitute this into the equation, without checkpoint, when we treat
一个中间神经网络我们需要三次前向传播，对吧？
one interregional neurork we get three forward, right?
但是如果我们无法进行检查点保存，其实每次完成一次中断或训练时，
But if we're unable to check pointing, we are actually every time we finish one inter or training,
我们都会向前推进四次。
we are spinning four times forward.
明白吗？这基本上就是MF和SF之间的关系。
Okay? That is basically the relation between MF and SF.
所以，当你无法进行检查点保存时，你会观察到一个相当高的F，
So um, like when you're unable to check pointing, you can observe a pretty high F,
但实际上，你的MF只有大约四分之三。明白了吗？
but indeed, your MF is only like three fourths. Okay?
好的，这部分有问题吗？好的，好的，好的。
Cool. Any problem on this one? Cool, cool, cool.
是的，这基本上就完成了我对这个非常非常重要概念的定义，
Yeah, that basically finish my definition of this very, very important concept, and,
那我们继续。
um, yeah, let's continue.
有了MF的引入，我们的目标可以简化，基本上我们就是要最大化MF，
With that, with the introduction of MF, our goal can be simplified, basically we want to maximize MF
同时受限于内存约束。
subject to memory constraints.
为什么？因为通信会降低MF，对吧？
Why? Because communication is slowing down MF, right?
所以我们想要最小化通信量，这等同于最大化MF。
So we want to minimize our communication, which is equivalent to maximize MF.
所以我们在部件添加中的最终目标，基本上就是要最大化MF，
So our eventual goal in part addition is basically, we want to maximize MF,
这就是我们唯一的目标。好的。
and this is our only goal. Okay.
嗯，是的，基本上就是这样，
Um, yeah, that basically,
我认为这就定义了一个问题，好吧，关于p加法。
I think define a problem, okay, of p addition.
接下来，我将更深入地探讨通信问题，好吗？
And next, I'm going to dive deeper into communication, okay?
呃，我想在前一页中，
Uh, I think in the previous side,
我说过，在机器学习中，我们基本上有两种通信方式
I said, in machine learning, we basically have two types of communication
一种是连接式，一种是点对点（P to P）。
connective and P to P. Okay.
Let's basically study them a little bit in case you don't know that before, okay?
So what is PTP?
I think this one everybody knows, okay?
So this is PTP, right.
You have two devices and you want the first device to send something to second device.
And in a PTB communication, um, you basically have a sender and a receiver and the sender tries to
initiate basically the communication happens by you first initiate some connection
between these two devices, right?
And then you ask the sender to send the content to receiver, okay? That's simple.
Yeah, very simple. I think whenever you take
任何关于网络的课程，我想你都会学到这个，对吧。
any course on networking, I think you learn this, right.
好的。但我觉得真正和我们相关的部分，基本上是连接通信。
Okay. But I think the part that really concerns us is basically connective communication.
什么是连接通信？
What is connective communication?
你们当中有多少人上过高性能计算（HPC）的课程？没有吗。好的。
How many of you have taken courses in HPC, high performance computing? No. Okay.
那我们花点时间来讲讲，好吗？
Then let's spend some time, okay?
嗯，所以基本上，连接通信是一个非常非常，
Um, so basically connective communication is a very very,
我会说是一个核心概念，
I would say central concept in
在高性能计算（HPC）中。
HPC, high performance computing.
基本上，40年前，当时人们还没有做机器学习，
So basically, 40 years ago, people when people are not doing machine learning,
他们基本上都在做高性能计算。
they are basically doing HPC.
他们试图建立这样一个超级计算中心来估算宇宙，
And they try to build this kind of like super computing center to estimate the universe,
来估算一些物理定律，是的。
to estimate some physical laws, yeah.
他们尝试用这种计算方式做很多事情。
And they try to do a lot with this kind of stuff they be computing.
这种连接式通信其实就是那时候发明的，对吧？那么……
And this connective communication is basically invented back then, okay? So what are the?
我举一个例子，这个例子你已经知道了。
I think I give one example that is this example, you already know.
这都是在两个设备之间做归约。
This is all reduced between two devices.
幕后发生的事情是，你基本上需要这样发送
And what happens behind the scenes, uh, you basically need this to send
这个和这个来发送这个，然后每个设备都做归约以得到这里的结果。
this and this to send this and then every device do the reduction in order to get here.
好的，如果你玩过pipeword，他们有这个界面，
Okay. Um if you ever played with pipeword and they have this interface,
DDP其实就是在幕后分布数据。
DDP distribute data per behind the scenes.
基本上在这个GDP里面，他们正在做一个归约操作，接下来我会解释。
Basically inside of this GDP they are doing this reduce, which I will explain next.
但从数学上来说，它到底在做什么？
But mathematically, what already is doing?
也就是说，在这个例子中你有四个设备，每个设备都会给出
That is, you are given four devices in this example, and each device is going to give
一个名字，我们称之为rank（秩）。
a name, which we call rank.
这里我有四个设备，从rank 0到rank 3，它们的初始状态是每个
Here I hold four devices from rank zero to rank three and their initial state is each
都有一份不同的数组副本。
have a different copy of array.
呃，数组的值也各不相同。
Uh, different values of array.
在这个例子中，分别是in0、in1、in2、in3，他们想要进行通信。
In this example is in zero in one in two in three, and they want to communicate.
他们想以一种方式通信，最终所有rank基本上
They want to communicate in a way that they will end up with all the ranks have basically
都拥有相同的输出数组副本，也就是out。
the same copy of the output array, which is out.
在这里，他们要求输出是所有这些输入数组的总和。
And here, they require the out to be the sum of all these in arrays.
好的。这基本上就是全归约操作。
Okay. That is basically all reduced.
好的，基本上你需要执行一种通信模式，
Okay. And basically, you need to perform a communicating pattern to
基本上是在这些进程之间移动内容。
basically move the contents between these ranks.
所以这些值会从这里变到那里，这就是全归约。
So the values of the risk change from here to here. That is all reduce.
明白了吗？我觉得你也可以从全归约的字面意思推断出它的含义，
Okay? I think you can also infer the meaning from the lanes all reduced,
所以我需要执行归约操作，并且这个归约需要在所有进程之间进行。
so I need to perform or reduce and this reduce need to be performed across all ranks.
这就是为什么叫做归约。明白了吗？
Is is why it's called reduce. Okay.
关于这个有问题吗？
Any question regarding this one?
很好，我们还有更多内容。
Cool. We have more.
这不仅仅是全部使用，我们还有广播操作。
It's not only all use, and we have broadcast.
我们有归约操作，我认为归约并不是全部使用，只是一个归约。
We have reduce, and I think reduce understands not all use, it's just one reduce.
我们有散播收集、归约散播和使用，你需要记住这些。
We have scatter gather, reduced scatter and use, you need to memorize all this.
抱歉。是的。这个操作的区域将在某些紧急系统中被用到。
Sorry. Yeah. Be area of this operation is going to be used somewhere in emergency systems.
我们一个一个来讲，好吗？
Let's go through this one by one, okay.
广播，非常容易理解，对吧？
Broadcast, very easy to understand, right?
所以某个进程有一个数组，然后那个进程要把这个数组广播到所有其他进程。
So some rank have array, and that rank is to broadcast that array across all other ranks.
这就是广播操作。
That is the broadcast.
所以从这张幻灯片你已经明白了，对吧。
So from this slide, you already get it, right.
所以在这张幻灯片中，这个进程零就是进程一。
So in this slide, the rank this rank zero is rank one.
我将使用从零开始的索引。
I will use the index starting from zero.
一号进程拥有数组，目标状态是一号进程，将数组广播到所有其他进程。
Rank one has the array the target state is rank one, broadcast the array across all other ranks.
明白了吗？这是之前的，这是更高的。很好，对吧。
Okay? And this is before and this upper. Good, right.
广播非常容易理解。
Broadcast very easy to understand.
Reduce 和 reduced one 不是 red，只是 reduced one。
Reduce and reduced one is not red just reduced one.
这里也是所有进程都有数组，我们希望把这些数组合并成
This is also where array all the ranks has array, and the west is we want to reduce the arrays into
一个进程，目标进程拥有这些数组的合并结果。
one rank rank that target rank has a reduction of the arrays.
这里我做了一点演示。
Here I generate a little bit.
在大多数情况下，基本上是求和，但有时候你可能想做一些
In most cases, it's basically submission, but sometimes you want to do some
其他的归约操作，比如你想把数值相乘。
other reduction operations for example, you want to time the value
一起做还是你想做别的事情。
altogether or you want to do something else.
这就是为什么大家称它为reduce。
That's why people call it reduce.
基本上，你就是想把它们合并。
Basically, you want to reduce them.
关于这个有问题吗？
Any question about this one?
好，下一个。基本上你可以看到，broadcast和reduce就像是反过来的。
Cool. Next one. So basically, you can see, broadcast and reduced over like a reverse.
如果你不做reduce，基本上就是broadcast和reduce的反向操作。
If you don't do reduce, is basically broadcast and reduce reverse.
是的，在broadcast中，你是从一个rank发送到所有其他rank，而在reduce中，
Yeah. In broadcast, you send from one rank to all other ranks and in reduce,
你是从所有rank发送到一个rank。
you send from all ranks to one rank.
好的。
Cool.
下一个，scatter。scatter我觉得你一看到图片就能立刻明白，对吧？
Next one, scatter. Scatter I think you can once I shoot the picture you immediately get it, right?
所以一个进程有一个数组，目标状态是我想把这个数组分散出去
So one rank has array, and the target state is that I want to scatter the array
分散到所有其他进程上，并确保每个进程都拥有数组的1/N，
across all other ranks and make sure each rank has one divided by N here,
这里N等于进程的数量。
N is equal to the number ranks.
好的，这就是scatter操作。
Okay. That is scatter.
对，就是把整个数组分发到每个进程。
Yeah. It's like a through that array, all the way to every rank.
对，scatter，就是这样。
Yeah, scatter. Yeah. Okay.
而gather本质上是scatter的反向操作。
And gather is essentially the reverse operation of scatter.
也就是说每个进程有数组的一部分，每个进程拥有数组的一部分。
That is each rank has a part of the array, one divided by part of the array portion of the array.
然后我想把所有部分收集到一个目标进程里。
And I want to basically gather all together into a target rank.
这样最终目标进程就拥有了整个数组，明白了吗？这就是gather操作。
So the eventual target rank has the whole array, okay? It's gather.
你明白了吧？
And you man get it, right?
所以基本上scatter和gather是相反的操作。
So basically scatter and gather the reverse.
好，有问题吗？
Okay. A question?
这些都是简单的例子。
Okay, these are simple ones.
我们来看一些更复杂的例子。
Let's go into some more complicated ones.
显然，那些带有连接操作的
And apparently, uh, those connective operations with
肯定比没有连接操作的更复杂，对吧？
is definitely more complicated than without, right?
下一个就是all gather。
So the next one is basically all gather.
All gather基本上就是我想要收集，但我想所有rank一起收集。
Okay? All gather is basically like I want to gather, but I want all ranks together.
这样理解就很简单了，对吧？
Okay? That's easy way to understand, right?
所以我理解我有一个turkey rank，这个turkey rank会收集所有的值，
So I gather I have a turkey rank, and the turkey rank is going to gather all the values,
来自原始的各个rank。
from the original ranks.
但all gather本质上
But all gather essentially
我需要把所有的rank都聚在一起。明白了。
I need all the ranks together. Okay.
所以基本上初始状态是每个rank拥有数组的1/N部分，
So basically the initial state is every rank has one divided by N part of the array,
但初始状态其实是所有rank都有整个数组。
but the initial state is all ranks have the whole array.
好的，这就是all gather。有问题吗？
Okay, this is all gather. Any question?
下一个是reduce scatter。
The next one, reduce scatter.
你已经明白了，它基本上就是我先做reduce然后再scatter。
And you already get it's basically like I first reduce and then I scatter.
所以基本上，最初每个rank都有整个数组，对吧？
So basically, initially, each rank basically has the who rate, right?
我的目标是首先把所有的值做一次归约。
And my goal is I first reduce all the values.
比如说，我拿到了每个rank的提交结果。
I get the submisson for example, for ranks.
然后我想确保每个rank最终都能分到提交结果的一部分，也就是一除以部分。
And then I want to make sure each rank eventually has one divided by part of
这就是归约散播（reduced scatter）。
the submission. That is reduced scatter.
本质上，我是先归约再分发。
Essentially, I first reduce and then scatter.
好的，好的。
Okay. Okay.
你可以想象，其实聚合（gather）和归约散播（reduced scatter）它们有点相反，对吧？
And you can imagine, basically, gather and reduced scatter, they are kind of reverse, right?
全部聚合（all gather）就是把所有东西都收集到一起。
All gather is that I gather all things together.
而归约散播则是我先归约再分发。
And reduced scatter is I first reduce and scatter.
对，挺酷的。嗯，F。
Yeah. Cool. Yeah. F.
是的，你可以这么做。
Yeah, you can do that.
是的，我会讲到这个。对。
Yeah, I'm going to cover that. Yeah.
但是你的主控不高效。对，对。
But your master is not efficient. Yeah, yeah.
好的。嗯。对，对，对。
Okay. Yeah. Yeah, yeah. Yeah.
对。
Yeah.
所以在PA二中，我让你介绍两个连接器。
So I PA two, I ask you to introduce two connectives.
一个是all reduce，另一个是all。
One is all reduce, the other is all.
好的，你要想办法实现这个。
Okay. You're going to figure out how to implement that.
如果你能匹配NPI，你会得到一个很好的加分点。
And if you are able to match NPI, you are going to get a pretty good bounce point.
明白了吗？酷。
Okay? Cool.
还有这个减少的槽口
And this reduced gutter
Aguer 和减少的槽口，它们是相反的。
Aguer and reduced gutter, they are reverse.
最终，你会把这些都简化
Eventually, you have this all reduced
这就是我提到最多的那个，好吗？
This is the one that I mentioned most, okay?
每个数组都有一个 Everyb 有一个数组，你想把它们合并然后
Every array has one Everyb has one array, and you want to reduce them and then make
确保最终状态，你要确保每个 Everyb 都有总和，有一个归约结果。
sure event eventual state, you want to make sure everyb has the sum, has a reduction.
好的，有关连接词有什么问题吗？
Okay. Any question regarding the connectives?
没有。我们继续吧。好的，那我再给你们一些背景知识。
No. Let's continue. Okay. So to give you a little bit more background.
就像我说的，这些连接操作起源于 HPC，高性能计算。
Like I said, the connective operations, they originated from HPC, high performance computing.
但你可以看到现在的机器就像 HPC 一样。
But you can see today machinary is like HPC.
是的，它基本上和高性能计算非常相似。
Yeah, it's basically very similar to HPC.
好，第一个事实是，连接式比点对点要昂贵得多，你可以想象得到，对吧？
Okay. The first fact is connective is much more expensive than PTP, you can imagine, right?
我总是让我的所有进程进行通信。
I'm always asking all my ranks to communicate.
而在点对点通信中，我只需要两个进程进行通信。
And in PTP I only need two ranks to communicate.
好的，当然，
Okay. And of course,
我已经给你一个解决方案了。
I already give you a solution.
所以在作业一中，抱歉，
So in homework one, sorry,
在作业二的第一题中，你其实可以实现你的连接式，只需用点对点通信即可。
I question one of homework two, you can actually implement your connective, just use PDP.
你可以分配调制解调器。就像你说的，基本上就是让这个进程发送，每个你都能搞清楚，
You can assign modem. Like you said, basically like this rank to send each, you figure out what's
正确的发送方式是什么，你想要到达那里。
the right way to send and you want to get there.
好的，40%，保证40分。
Okay, 40% 40 points guaranteed.
好的，非常简单，对吧？但这样会非常慢。
Okay, very easy, right? But that's going to be very slow.
是的，当然。好的。
Yeah, of course. Yeah. Okay.
Connected在过去20年里得到了高度优化。
Connected is highly optimized in the past 20 years.
如果你看到任何以CCL结尾的库，
If you look out for any library that is ending with CCL,
CCL代表连接通信库（Connective Communication Library）。
CCL stands for connective Communication Library.
X基本上是制作这个库的公司的品牌名。
X basically is the branding of that company making this library.
例如，当X等于N时，就是DR CCL，你明白了吗？
For example, when X is equal to N, it is DR CCL you got it.
当X等于M时，你不知道那是什么。
W X equal to M, you don't know what is.
好的，我也不知道。
Okay, I also don't know.
当Xc one基本上就是英特尔的时候，明白吗？
When Xc one is basically Intel, okay?
这是英特尔的CCR。
This is Intel CCR.
呃，其实是代表微软。对。
Uh, actually stands for Microsoft. Yeah.
微软也有CCO。
Microsoft has CCO as well.
所以基本上，在过去40年里，每家公司都在开发自己的CCO。
So basically, in the past 40 years, every company is developing a CCO.
是的。我觉得谷歌也有CCO，但我不知道名字是什么，是内部的，好吗？
Yeah. I think Google also has a CCO, but I don't know what's the name. It's internal, okay?
嗯，你刚才问我为什么Odia的股价这么好，对吧？
Um, and you asked me why Odia stock price is so good, right?
部分原因是因为NCCO是最好的之一。
One partial reason is because NCCO is one of the best.
好的？所以Odia在优化其连接通信库方面做得相当不错。对。
Okay? So Odia did pretty well on optimizing its connective communicing libraries. Yeah.
所以基本上NCR库也是最好的之一。
And there so basically NCR library is one of the best.
所以每家公司都在为MIDI Ds做这件事。
So every company is doing that, o for MIDI Ds.
但是连接式通信有一个很糟糕的特点，就是它不具备容错性。
But connective communication has a pretty bad property that is not fault tolerant.
也就是说，每次你在所有设备之间发起通信时，如果有一个设备出错，
That is every time when you initiate communication across all devices, if one device failed,
那么这次通信就会失败。
that communication is going to fail.
它不具备容错性。
It's not fault tolerant.
这就是为什么现在，如果你加入一家做大模型训练的公司，
That's why today, if you join a company doing big model training,
你的工作大部分时间都在看护GPU。
your job mostly is spending time on babysiting or GPUs.
你需要确保没有GPU报错。
You need to make sure there's no GPU, throwing out arrows.
否则，你的整个任务都会被中断。
Otherwise, your entire job is going to be stopped.
好的，明白。有问题吗？好的。
Okay. Cool. Any question? Okay.
我们基本上可以了解连接通信中发生了什么。
We basically get a picture of what is going on in connective communication.
接下来我会介绍一些算法，基本上可以让
Then I'm going to introduce a few algorithms to basically make
这种通信运行得非常快。
this communication operates pretty fast.
但在介绍这些算法之前，
But before I introduce the algorithms,
我想先建立一些数学基础。
I want to first establish a little bit of mathematical foundation.
那么你要如何理解正在发生的事情呢？
So how you can understand what is going on?
比如通信应该有多慢或多快。
Like how slow or how fast communication should be.
好吗？在通信中，我们基本上使用这个字母表模型。
Okay? So in communication, we basically use this alphabet model.
好，这个模型就叫做字母表。
Okay. This model is just called alphabet.
原因是因为它有两个参数，α 和 β。
The reason is because it has two parameters and bet.
好吗？所以基本上在网络通信中，当我们描述通信速度时，
Okay? So basically in networking, when we characterize the speed of communication,
我们基本上使用这个字母模型，速度是
we basically use this alphabet model and the speed is
基本上被描述为Alpha加上十倍的提升。
basically characterized as Apha plus ten times better.
好的？这里的Alpha基本上就是延迟。
Okay? So here, Alpha is basically the latency.
也就是说，如果我想在任意两个节点之间发起通信，
That is, if I want to launch a communication between any two ranks,
我会受到延迟的影响。
I'm suffering a latency.
就像从内核到GPU一样，
It's like to a kernel to GPU,
我会受到延迟的影响，而且这个延迟是恒定的。
I suffer a latency, and the latency is constant.
只要我需要通信，
As long as I need to communicate,
我就需要初始化套接字，
I need to initiate the sockets,
我需要做这种繁重的工作，这需要时间。
I need to do this kind of heavy lifting work, and that takes time.
明白了吗？这就是 Alpha。这部分其实非常容易理解，对吧？
Okay? That's Alpha. And this part is basically very easy to understand, right?
所以这个 beta 基本上就是一除以 B，B 是带宽。
So this beta is basically one divided by B and B is bandwidth.
带宽，也就是这两个节点之间的通信带宽。
Bandwidth. That is the communicating bandwidth between these two ranks.
那这个带宽由什么决定呢？由硬件，对吧？
And this bandwidth was determined by what? By hardware, right?
所以你可以花更多的钱去买更高的带宽。
So you can spend more money to buy more bandwidth.
这样这个值就会变大，对吧？
That will make this one bigger, right?
呃，第二部分本质上就像，这里是消息的大小。
Uh, the second part is essentially like, this is a message size.
也就是你想在节点之间发送的数据量。
That is how much you want to send between the ranks.
很明显，你用带宽去除以它，就得到了基本上传输所花的时间。
And apparently, you divide by bandwidth, you get the time spent on, basically sending,
嗯，就是这个消息，对吧？
um this message, right?
这就是直观地解释这个字母模型的方法，好吗？
That's how that basically intuitively explain this alphabet model, okay?
总结一下，当你开始一次通信时，你首先会受到带宽的影响，
So to summarize, when you start a communication, you first suffer bandwidth,
还会有一个固定的延迟，然后剩下的时间取决于
suffer a latency, constant latency, and then the rest of time is determined by
你想发送的消息大小以及你拥有的带宽，好吗？
how much the message size you want to send and the bandwidths you have, okay?
有了这个模型，你基本上可以，呃，呃，尝试分析一下，对吧？
With this model, you can basically, uh, uh, try to analyze it a little bit, right?
所以如果你要发送一个非常小的消息，非常小的消息，比如只有一个字节。
So if you are going to send a very small message, a very small message, just one byte.
那么在这个公式中，这个Rhi将会占主导地位，Rp也会占主导地位。
So in this equation, this Rhi is going to dominate Rp dominate.
但如果你要发送一个很大的消息，随着消息大小趋近于无穷大，
But if you are going to send a large message as, then see an approach infinity,
那么这个项就会占主导地位。
then this term is going to dominate.
这个延迟是一个专业术语。
And this latency is a smart term.
好的。我之所以强调这一点，是因为当你发送一个很小的信息时，
Okay. The reason I emphasize this is because, um, when you send a small message size,
你希望尽量减少这个延迟，对吧？
uh, you want to minimize this phone, right?
然后当你发送一个很大的信息时，你要确保能够充分利用所有带宽。
And then when you send a large message, you want to make sure you utilize all the bandwidth.
明白了。
Okay.
基于这个观察，在高性能计算领域，他们基本上花了很多时间来优化连接方式，
And given this observation, in the HPC community, they basically spent a lot of
并且开发了两种实现和算法，
time optimizing the connectives, and they develop two types of implementations and algorithms to
以加快连接通信的速度。
make connective communication fast.
其中一种算法主要强调延迟，也就是说他们假设你要发送小的信息，
And one type of algorithm basically emphasize latency, that is they assume that you
并且他们希望确保能够最小化这个延迟。
are going to send small messages, and they want to make sure they minimize this
另一种类型，他们基本上想要最大化带宽的利用率，
pa. And the other type, they want to, uh basically maximize the utilization of bandwidth,
并且他们假设你会发送很大的消息。
and they assume that you are going to send big messages.
好的，我会介绍这两种方式，你可以在作业中选择实现其中一种。
Okay, I'm going to introduce both, and you can choose to implement either one in your homework.
但让我先问一个问题。
But let me ask a question.
在沉浸式学习中，更倾向于哪一种？
Immersion learning, which one is preferred?
沉浸式学习中，你觉得哪一种更有可能占主导地位？抱歉。
Immersion learning, do you think which one is likely to dominate? Sorry.
从情感上来说，你是在不同DP之间发送很大的张量，显然情感上你更倾向于这种方式。
Emotionally, you are sending big tensors across DPs and apparently emersionaly, you prefer this one.
你更希望最小化这种方式。
You prefer to minimize this one.
但我还是会花时间介绍这两种方式。
But I will still take time to introduce both.
下面再补充一点背景知识。
So a little bit more background.
第一种试图最小化距离的算法
So the first type of algorithm that try to minimize distance
被称为最小生成树算法。
is called minimum spanning tree algorithm.
第二种强调带宽的算法被称为环算法。
The second type of algorithm that try to emphasize bandwidth is called ring algorithm.
这就是为什么有时候人们在说 all-reduce 时总是称之为 ring all-reduce。
That's why sometimes when people speak or reduce the always called ring or reduce.
是的。在过去的二十年里，HPC 社区培养了很多并行计算的学生，
Yeah. In the past 20 years, this HPC community, they have graduated many many PE students and they
他们在 OpenMP 上写了很多论文。
wrote so many papers on opens.
2023 年，我记得图灵奖颁给了一位 HPC 教授，对吧？
In 2023, I think the Turing award was given to HPC professor, okay?
很酷。那么我们先来讲第一种类型，好吗？
Cool. So let's come to the first type, okay?
在第一种类型中，我们想要最小化延迟。
In the first time, we want to minimize the latency.
好吗？为了最小化延迟，Alpha，你有什么直观的想法？
Okay? In order to minimize the latency, the Apha, what's the high intuition?
我们希望最小化通信所需的错误次数，
Le want to minimize the number of wrongs needed for communication,
因为每次你发起通信时，你都会受到ARpa的影响。
Because every time when you launch your communication, you are going to suffer ARpa.
所以你想要最小化通信的轮数。
So you want to minimize the number of pans.
明白了吗？在这个最小轮次进入算法中，思路是这样的。
Okay? In this minimum span entry algorithm, the idea is like this.
信息从一个等级开始。
So the message starts on one rank.
一个处理器。
One processor.
然后我们尝试把所有的等级分成两半。
And then we try to divide all the ranks into half.
这就是为什么它被称为最小生成树。
That's why it's called a minimum spanning tree.
我们基本上尝试把所有的等级分成前半部分和后半部分。
We try to basically divide all the ranks into first half and second half.
我们要做的就是把消息从前半部分发送到后半部分。
And what we do is basically we send the message from the first half to the second half.
在这个例子中，我把一条消息发送到网络中没有这条消息的那一半。
In this example, I send a message to the half of a network that does not contain this message.
对吧？所以在这里，我把进程分成了这一组和那一组。
Right? So here, I divide the ranks into this group and this group.
我发现我的初始进程基本上在这一组里。
I found that my initial rank is basically in this group.
而在第二组里，没有这样的消息。
And in the second group, there's no such message.
我的第一步是试图把消息从这里发到那里。
My first step is I'm trying to send this to here.
明白了吗？一旦我完成这一步，我该做什么？
Okay? And once I finish this step, what I do?
基本上我会用二叉树消息传递的方法。
I basically use binary tree message.
我的做法是，一旦这些进程拥有了这条消息，
What I do is once the ranks have this message,
我知道这组和那组里，都有一个进程包含了消息，
I know this group and this group, they all have a rank which contains a message,
然后我会递归地继续这么做。
and I'm going to do that recursively.
好吗？我要这样做，可以吗？
Okay? I'm going to It's like this, okay?
然后我会再把它分开。
And then I'm going to divide it again.
我会在这里分一下，对吧，然后我会在这里分一下。
I'm going to divide here, right, and I'm going to divide here.
好吗？我要让这个降到这里，这个再传到这里。
Okay? I'm going to let this descend to this and this to send this.
我会递归地做这件事。
And I do it recursively.
我可以证明这样会最小化R，因为这是最小生成树，并且
And I can prove that this will minimize R because this is a minimum span entry and the number
我需要的次数是保证最小的。
once I needed is guaranteed is minimized.
好的。
Okay.
给你一个更实际的例子，我们来用最小生成树做广播。
To give you more realistic example, let's run this minimum spanning tree for Broadcast.
还记得广播吧？
Okay. Still remember broadcast, right?
这是之前，这是之后。
This is before, this is after.
那我们怎么做呢？我们从初始状态开始。
So how do we do that? So we start from the initial state.
我们尝试把所有的进程分组。
We try to divide all the ranks.
明白了吗？
Okay?
我们把所有进程分成两组。
And we divide all ranks into two groups.
不包括那个需要把数值发送到第二组其他进程的进程。
Without the rank that has the value to send its value to another rank at the second group.
然后我们继续在每一组中分组。
And we continue divided ranks in each group.
然后我们同步，对吧？
And we sin, right?
我们继续像这样广播这些数值，明白了吗？
And we continue to basically broadcast these values like this, okay?
你可以说经过四步之后，
And you can say after four steps,
基本上我有八个进程都有消息，对吧？
I basically have eight ranks having a message, right?
然后我发现还有一个进程没有收到消息，所以我再执行一步。
And I found out there's one rank that is still missing message, so I perform one more step.
明白了吗？我可以证明，发起通信所需的步骤是最少的
Okay? And I can prove that the steps needed to initiate the communication is minimized
使用这棵生成树。
using this spanning tree.
明白了吗？所以这个算法基本上就是用来最小化 Alpha 项的，好吗？
Okay? That's why this algorithm is basically used for minimize Alpha term, okay?
有什么问题吗？没问题。好的。
Any question? Cool. Okay.
嗯，现在我们来探索一下。
Um, now let's try to explore.
顺便说一下，你们可以忽略这些方程。
By the way, you can ignore these equations.
好的，我不会讲这些，考试也不会考。
Okay. I'm not going to cover this, and it's not covered in exam.
好的，但原因是
Okay. But the reason
我之所以有这张幻灯片，是因为我想探讨不同连接操作之间的一些联系。
I have this slide is because I want to explore some connections between
不同的连接操作。
different connective operations.
大家还记得gather操作的初始和结束状态吧？
Gather gather still remember the initial end state, right?
也就是说，每个进程都有自己的数据，然后丢弃整个全局数组。
So in is each rank has protein and ditch the entire global array.
实现gather的一种方式是，我们可以先进行gather操作，对吧？
So one way that we can realize or gather is we can we can first gather, right?
我们可以先执行一次gather操作。
We can first perform a gather.
也就是把所有的值收集到一个目标进程上。
So we gather the values into one target rank.
然后我们再做一次广播，对吧？
And then we do a broadcast, right?
所以基本上，or gather等于gather加上broadcast。
So basically, uh, or gather equals to gather plus broadcast.
很好，reduce scatter，从名字你们应该已经知道了。
Cool. Reduce scatter, uh, you already know from the name.
所以你首先要这样做归约，然后再做分散。
So you first reduce like this, and then you do a scatter.
是的，你得做归约分散。
Yeah, you got to reduce scatter.
或者归约。有人能给我一个答案吗？
Or reduce. Can anyone give me an answer?
怎么组合或者归约？
How to assemble or reduce?
对，你先做归约，然后再做广播。
Yes, you do reduce and then you do broadcast.
明白了吗？所以基本上在最后这种情况下，人们实现这三种操作的方式，
Okay? So basically in this last scenario, the way people implement these three opportunity,
基本上，他们首先实现那些基础操作，然后再把它们组合起来。
basically, they first implement those primitive ones and they assemble it.
好的。
Okay.
所以总结一下，归约分散就是通过分散来实现归约，或者归约就是归约，
So in summary, reduced gutter is reduced by scatter or reduce is reduced and
广播或者收集通常就是收集和广播。
broadcast or gather is usually gather and bracast.
对，没错。你明白我的意思了吧？
Yeah. Exactly. You got the point, right?
这基本上就引出了第二部分，但我想先回答你的问题。
So that will basically bring us to the second part, but I want to answer your question first.
这个算法，它最小化了通信的次数。
So this algorithm, it minimizes the number one to communicate.
但它并没有利用带宽，对吧？
But it does not utilize the bandwidth, right?
因为每个节点只向一个目标节点发送数据。
Because each node only send to a target node.
当这个节点在发送时，其他带宽都没有被利用。
And while this node is sending all the other bandwidths are not utilized.
明白了吗？
Okay?
很好。就像我说的，这种方式在想象中并不是首选，因为它最小化了 alpha 项，
Cool. Like I said, this one is not preferred Imaginaring, because it's minimize the alpha term,
但反过来，第二项就变大了。
but inverse ing the second term is larger.
所以我现在要带大家进入第二部分，好吗？
So I'm going to bring all you into the second part, okay?
但在那之前，我们先总结一下MST，好吗？
But before that, let's summarize MST, okay?
所以MST在小消息场景下非常有用，因为第一个项占主导，对吧？
So for MST, is extremely useful for small messages where the first term is dominating, right?
它强调了最小生成树算法中的一个问题，
And it emphasizes tiency the problem of minimum span entry algorithm is that it
就是它优先考虑了alpha项，而不是更优的项。
prioritize the alpha term than a better term.
就像那位同学指出的，特别是在通信的初始阶段，
So like that student pointed out, when especially at the initial stage of the communication,
大多数互连都是空闲的。
most of the interconnects are idle.
你实际上并没有利用这里的带宽，对吧？
You are not actually utilize the bandwidth here, okay?
接下来我要运行另一个算法，就是环形算法，
And next, I'm going to run another algorithm which is ring algorithm,
这个环形算法其实就是我今天在机器上用的那个，好吗？
and this ring algorithm is essentially the one that I used today in macheary, okay?
这个环形算法的基本原则就是我们尽量利用所有这些链路，
And the general principle of this ring algorithm is that we try to utilize all these links,
我们尝试利用所有这些在各个节点之间可用的带宽。
and we try to utilize all these band ways available between ranks.
假设所有节点都通过类似于Iranet之类的网络连接在一起。
Let's assume that all the ranks are connected using some like Iranet or whatever.
好吗？在这里，通信的轮数并不重要。
Okay? And here, how many rounds of communication does not matter.
因为就像我说的，Alpha已经不再重要了。
Because like I said, the Alpha does not matter anymore.
主要的开销在于第二项更大。
The main overhead is the second term better.
所以，有一种算法可以实现这个目标，基本上我们尝试在所有节点之间形成一个逻辑环。
So, one algorithm that enable this basically we try to form a logical ring across all ranks
然后我们沿着这个环发送消息。明白吗？
and we send messages along this ring. Okay?
我们来看看具体怎么做。
Let's see, how we do that.
这里是初始状态，比如我们想要执行，比如说，
So here, this is the initial state where we want to perform, for example, um,
类似于gather gather这样的操作。明白吗？
like gather gather, something like that. Okay?
所以我们基本上可以像这样构建一个逻辑环，对吧？
So we can basically construct a logical ring like this, right?
这里你可以看到，这个rank有这部分。
So here you can see, this rank has this part.
这个rank有这部分，这个un有这部分。
This rank has this part. This un has this part.
那我们要做的就是尽可能利用带宽。
So what do we do is we want to utilize the bandari as much as possible.
所以我们要确保任何时候所有的rank都在发送或接收，好吗？
So at anytime we want to make sure all the ranks are sending or receiving, okay?
那我们要做的就是构建这个环。
So what do we do we construct this ring.
在下一步，我们需要每个rank把这个数据发送给下一个rank。
And in the next step, we need each rank to send this protein to the next rank.
对吧？通过这样做，
Right? And by doing this,
我可以确保所有的rank都很忙，至少在网络配对上是这样。
I can make sure that all ranks are busy, at least on networking pair.
好吗？如果我们这样做，基本上我们就完成了一轮消息交换。
Okay? So if we do this, what happen is basically we perform one round of exchanging messages,
对，然后我们到这里。
right, and we get here.
好吗？你可以比较这两种状态之间的差异，对吧。
Okay? You can compare the difference between these two states, right.
这里的关键区别是所有设备都在忙于通信。
The key difference here is all devices are busy on communicating.
这就是为什么我们可以利用带宽，对吧？
That's why we can utilize bandwiys, okay?
接下来你要做的基本上就是继续传播这些消息，对吗？
And what you do next is basically you continue to propagate these messages, right?
你可以构建另一个环，然后继续这样做。
And you can construct another ring and you continue doing this.
在你进行了很多很多轮之后，你最终会达到一种状态。
And after you doing many, many rounds, you eventually get to a state
基本上，我接下来要演示一下。
where so basically, I'm going to shoot next.
好吗？
Okay?
我接下来要演示，并且我会在几个连接上运行这种算法。
I'm going to shoot next, and I'm going to run this kind of algorithm on a few connectives.
好的。那么我们来做一次gather，或者说我们来做一个ring gather。
Yeah. So gather, let's run a ring or gather.
好吗？所以我们从左边开始，试图到达右边，对吧？
Okay? So we start from the left hand side and we try to reach the right hand side, right?
这是我们的初始状态，对吧，我们先构建一个环，
So this are initial state, right, we construct a ring, and
然后每个rank把这个蛋白质发送到下一个rank。
we each rank to send this protein to the next rank.
嗯，这就是一轮通信，对吧，我们到这里了。
Uh, This is the one round of communication, right we get here.
然后我们再进行一轮，好吗？
Then we run another round, okay?
我们就到这里了，对吧？
We'll get to here, right?
再来一轮，再来一轮，第三轮。
Another round here, another round here, ther round.
好的，我们搞定了，对吧？你明白我的意思了吧。很棒。
Okay, we're good, right? So you got me right. Cool.
你可以看到，这个可视化效果很好，但问题在于每一步……
And you can see, this is a pretty good visualization, but the problem here is at each step,
你在占用带宽，但你需要运行很多很多次，
you are utilizing bandwidth, but you are taking many many runs,
和最小生成树相比呢？
compared to the minimum spanning tree?
因为最小生成树，你是在做二叉树，非常快。
Because minimum spanning tree, you are doing a binary tree, which is super fast.
但在这个算法中，你基本上需要运行的次数等于等级的数量，
But in this algorithm, you basically need to run the number of times equal to the number of ranks,
也就是更多的运行次数。
which is more runs.
所以我们要稍微增加一下Alpha项，但没关系，因为就像我说的，
So the Alpha term we are going to increase a little bit, but it doesn't matter because like I said,
第二项是主导的，对吧？
the second term dominates, okay?
我们来运行另一个版本，reduce scatter。
Let's run another version, reduce scatter.
还记得reduce scatter吧？
Still remember reduce scatter, right?
所以我们首先进行reduce和scatter。
So we first reduce and scatter.
那么我们要做的是，这就是我们的联合状态，对吧。
So what do we do is, this is our united state, right.
我们想要减少它们并分散结果。
We want to reduce them and scatter results.
所以我们构建了一个环。
So we construct a ring.
在这部分消息上，我们执行一次归约操作。
On on this part of this message, we perform a reduce.
然后我们继续这样做，把结果发送出去。
And we continue doing so we send the results.
我们传播以减少结果，明白吗？
We propagated to reduce the results, okay?
一旦我们传播，基本上每个节点都会有一个部分和，然后我们继续归约和传播，
Once we propagate basically each we will have a partial sum and we continue to reduce and propagate,
归约，传播，归约，传播。
reduce, propagate, reduce propagate.
好的。我们会得到结果。
Okay. We'll get results.
是的，酷。这基本上就是一个环形算法。
Yeah. Cool. This is basically a ring algorithm. Okay.
那么在这个环形算法下，我们也来做一些不同连接操作之间的关联。
Then under this ring algorithm, let's also do some connection between different connectives.
好的。
Okay.
所以基本上对于这个广播操作，我们可以用这个算法从基本操作来组装，
So basically for this broadcast, we can basically use this algorithm to as assemble from primitives,
基本上广播等于，我们先做分发，然后再做收集。
basically broadcast equals to, uh we first scatter, and then we gather.
所以广播等于分发加收集，对吧？
So broadcast is equal to scattering or gather, okay?
对于这个归约操作，我们的做法是，首先做归约分发，然后再做收集，
And for this reduced one, what we do is basically we first do a reduced scatter, and then we gather,
归约分发和收集。
reduce scatter and gather.
基本上我们就是这样得到的。
We basically um, get this one.
对于归约操作，我们也有不同类型的组合方式。
For reduce, we also have a different types of combination.
为了用这个环形算法实现归约操作，
In order to implement or reduce using this ring algorithm,
我们基本上做的第一步是减少散射，减少多余的散射，
what we do is basically we first reduce scatter, reduce the redundant scatter,
然后我们再进行聚合。
and then we do gather.
好的。
Okay.
所以简单总结一下，在这个环形算法中，reduce 等于 reduce Getter 加上 gather，
So to summarize a little bit, uh, in this ring, algorithm, reduce equals to reduce Getter
all reduce 等于 reduce Getter 加上 all gather，
plus gather and all reduced equals reduce Getter plus or gather
广播等于 scatter 加上 all gather。
and broadcast equals to Scatter and all gather.
有问题吗？如果你在这里有点困惑，
An An question? Okay, if you feel a little bit confused here,
看一下，复习一下我的幻灯片就好了。
look, just, you know, review my slides.
我觉得这里讲得很清楚。
I think it's pretty clear here.
我之所以想要建立这个联系，是因为，你知道，
The reason I try to draw this connection is because, uh, you know,
下周当我们开始介绍机器部分时，你们都要明白
next week when we start introducing machinery partism, you all understand you all
意识到其实我们基本上是在分解这些所有的归约操作
realize that basically we are basically decomposing all these all reduced
并且将广播和归约操作分解成不同的基本操作，然后我们会尝试调度它们
and broadcast and reduced into different primitives, and we'll try to schedule them in
在不同的执行位置。
different places of execution.
这样会导致不同的内存利用率、不同的内存需求，
Okay. And that will result into different memory utilization, different memory requirement, and
还有不同的计算模式。
also different computer patterns.
好的。
Cool.
嗯，我觉得我们快要讲完这张幻灯片、这节课了。
Um, I think we're pretty close to finish this slide, finish this lecture.
那我们回来一下。
So let's come back.
好的，我们把这个放到机器部分的背景下来说一说。
Okay, let's basically ground this in the context of Machining Pism, okay.
就像我说的，互操作总是导致PTV通信，这其实很明显。
So like I said, interop always results in PTV communication, and this is quite obvious.
现在，你们可能会开始问，为什么互操作总是导致连接性的通信。
Now, you probably start asking why interop always result in connective communication.
好吗？这是下周一个非常重要的话题，但我想在这节课结束前，
Okay? And this is a pretty important topic for next week, but I want to finish this lecture
给你们讲一下，呃，基本上，把游行主义和我花了差不多半小时介绍的连接词之间的联系，
by giving you some connection between, uh, basically, um, marching Pism and the connectives,
我花了将近半个小时来介绍这些内容，好吗？
I spend almost half an hour introducing, okay?
所以，互操作总是导致不同类型的
So the reason that intraop always result into different sorts
连接性通信的原因是，呃，至少在这个repenton机制下，
of connective communication is because, um, um, at least under this repenton mechanism,
就像我介绍的，基本上是给节点和操作符上色。
like I introduced basically coloring nodes and operators.
你会发现，当我们做这个互操作划分时，实际上是在划分
You realize that when we do this intraop partism, we are essentially partition
操作符及其输出。
the operators and its output.
每当发生通信时，都是因为我们需要重新分区。
Whenever a communication happens, it happens because we need to repartition it.
好的。记住，在张量并行的情况下，就是我刚才讲解的那种情况。
Okay. Remember, in the tensor parallel case, that is the one that I run through.
所以当通信模式，呃，发生时，
So when the communication patterns, uh when or happens,
基本上每个rank都会得到一个部分和，
it's basically each rank basically get a partial sum,
但你希望每个rank都有一个副本，对吧。
but you want each rank to have a replica, right.
这意味着你需要以某种方式交换数组内容，
Which means that you need to swap the array content in a way
以满足重新分区的需求。
that to meet the repartitioning requirement.
好的。在下一节课中，
Okay. And in the next lecture,
我将展示，呃，基本上在我们今天用来
I'm going to show that uh basically in all types of existing pysms that we use to
训练语言模型或任何其他模型的所有现有pysm类型中。
train language models or train whatever models today.
好的，只有当两个操作符，也就是相邻的两个操作符之间，
Okay. Uh, the communicating happens only when that between two operators, two adjacent operators,
他们的分区方案不同时，才需要进行通信。
their partitioning scheme are different.
明白了吗？为了满足下一个操作符的分区方案，你必须对数组进行重新分区。
Okay? In order to meet the partiing scheme of the next operator, you have to repar in array.
好的，这里我举了两个案例的例子，但实际上这是一个四维的情况。
Okay? So here, I give you an example in two decase but in reality, this is a 40 case.
以Transformer为例，你有一个四维数组，B乘T乘H乘其他维度，对吧？
F doming transformer, you have a 40 array B times times H times something else, right?
我们稍微简化一下，好吗？
And let's simplfy a little bit, okay.
在两个案例中，我们有三种分区方式，对吧？
In two cases, we have three types of partitioning, right?
第一种是复制分区。
The first type is replicated.
就是每个设备都有一份副本。
That I device have a replica.
好的，第二种是行分区。
Okay? The second is row partition.
所以是横向切分。
So horizontal cut.
好吗？第三种类型是列分区。
Okay? And the third type is column partition.
就像我说的，通信发生在你需要在这三种状态之间切换的时候，对吧？
Like I said, the communication happens when you need to switch between these three states, right?
有时候一个算子需要副本，有时候一个算子需要行分区，
Sometimes one operator need a replica, sometimes one operator need a row party,
有时候一个算子需要列分区。
sometimes one opportun a column partition.
然后我开始问一个问题，好吗？
Then I start to ask a question, okay?
那如果我想从行分区切换到副本，我该怎么做？
So if I want to switch from row party to replicate what I do.
那如果我想从这里到这里画一条边，我该怎么做？
So if I want to draw a edge from here to here what I do.
基本上就是用gather，对吧？
It's basically for gather, right?
所以你想让每个设备都收集它的部分，对吧？
So you want each device to gather it protein, right?
然后你会得到一个副本。好的。
And then you will get a replica. Okay.
下一个问题是，如果我想从副本切换到行Pisin，
And the next one is if I want to switch from replica to row Pisin,
也就是说，我想做一个反向操作。
that is, I want to do a reverse what I do.
散布，真的吗？再想想。我什么都不做。
A scatter, really? Think twice. I do nothing.
我只是把它扔掉，对吧？我不需要通信。
I just throw it away, right? I don't need to communicate.
为什么？因为我想在这两个状态之间切换，对吧？
Why? Because I want to switch between from this state to this state, right?
所以现在，每个已经有了一个副本，而我最终的状态
So now, each already have a replica and my eventual state
我希望每个状态只保留一半。
I want each state to only have a half.
我只是把另一半扔掉。
I just throw the other half.
我不需要通信。明白了吗？
I don't need to communicate. Okay?
我什么都不做。好吗？切片。对，我会切片。好吗？
I do nothing. Okay? Slice. Yeah, I do slice. Okay?